No longer needed?
Sudah cukup?
What do you mean by that, Mr. Schuwald?
Apa maksudmu, Pak Schuwald?
I'm saying that the investigation I asked you to do is now over.
Maksudku penyidikan yang kuminta disudahi saja.
Hold on a second.
Tunggu sebentar.
Yes, the investigation on Karl Neuman is done.
Penyidikan terhadap Karl Neuman memang sudah selesai.
He was your son.
Dia adalah putra kandungmu.
You have my gratitude.
Terima kasih.
Wait, hold on.
Sebentar, tunggu dulu.
That doesn't mean everything is resolved.
Bukan berarti semua beres.
There's a possibility that Edmund Fahren did not die by suicide.
Ada kemungkinan Edmund Fahren tidak mati bunuh diri.
We don't know who was pulling the strings behind Fahren.
Kita tak tahu siapa dalang di balik kematian Fahren.
Everything has been resolved.
Semuanya beres.
The tea is ready, Father.
Tehnya sudah siap, Ayah.
Oh, I see.
Baiklah.
Would you like some too?
Kau juga mau teh?
Oh no, I'm fine.
Tidak perlu.
Thank you for everything.
Terima kasih atas kerjanya.
Send me your bill.
Kirimkan saja tagihannya.
What nice weather today.
Hari ini cuacanya bagus.
Yes.
Ya.
Johan is here too.
Johan juga di sini.
I see. Johan is also here?
Oh, ya? Johan juga di sini?
Can a cold-hearted man who trusts no one and keeps everyone at a distance
Mungkinkah pria berhati dingin yang sulit percaya dan tak mau didekati
transform into a good-natured old man just from finding his son?
berubah jadi orang tua ramah setelah bertemu putranya?
That smile…
Senyum itu…
It's hard to believe that man was called the Vampire of Bavaria.
Sulit dipercaya pria itu pernah dijuluki Vampir dari Bayern.
"I see. Johan is also here?" Is that so?
"Oh, ya? Johan juga di sini?"
So, now you're running around looking for this puppy, huh?
Jadi, kau sibuk mencari anak anjing ini?
Yes, it seems my client's ex-husband took off with it.
Ya, sepertinya dibawa kabur mantan suami klienku.
Looks like custody disputes over puppies can be difficult too.
Perselisihan hak asuh anak anjing juga rumit, ya?
Good grief.
Rumit sekali.
Sorry, but I'm going to have some wine.
Maaf, aku mau minum anggur.
Go right ahead.
Silakan.
Water is enough for me.
Aku cukup minum air saja.
You say work has slowed down,
Katamu pekerjaan mulai santai,
but you also don't seem tempted by alcohol.
tapi kau juga tak tergoda alkohol.
Yes, it's all okay on that front.
Ya, masalah alkohol jangan khawatir.
On that front?
Masalah alkohol?
Is there something else bothering you then?
Ada masalah lain yang mengusikmu?
Well, I have some free time, so I end up doing stupid things.
Ada waktu luang, jadi aku melakukan hal tak penting.
I end up looking at personal scrapbooks I made in my police detective days.
Aku membaca catatan pribadiku saat jadi penyidik.
About unsolved cases.
Catatan kasus tak terpecahkan.
I see.
Begitu.
And how do you feel when you look at them?
Bagaimana rasanya melihat catatan itu?
Frustrated.
Aku kesal
With those murder cases and this one,
mengingat kasus di catatan dan yang saat ini kuselidiki.
when I think about how those criminals are living comfortably in this world,
Karena para pembunuhnya masih hidup nyaman di dunia,
I just can't bear how incapable I am.
aku frustrasi dengan ketidakmampuanku.
You were capable.
Kau mampu.
But Richard, you'd get too caught up in your cases
Tapi, Richard, kau terlalu terlibat
and identify too much with them.
dan terlalu peduli dengan kasus-kasusmu.
You'd get frustrated that you couldn't see what the culprit was thinking…
Kau frustrasi tak bisa memahami pola pikir pelaku.
So I ran to alcohol.
Sampai alkohol jadi pelarian.
Yes, that's right.
Ya, benar.
Thank you for waiting.
- Terima kasih sudah menunggu. - Makanannya tiba.
But I don't think it's a bad thing
Tapi menurutku itu bukan hal buruk,
that you look at scrapbooks from your old cases.
melihat catatan pribadi tentang kasus lamamu.
It just makes me more frustrated.
Aku malah makin frustrasi.
No, it's fine now.
Tak apa-apa.
Tell me what thoughts you have when you see them from your current perspective.
Ceritakan pemikiranmu saat melihatnya dengan perspektif sekarang.
You were drunk and killed that young serial killer.
Kau mabuk saat menghabisi pembunuh berantai muda itu.
You are ready now to face that truth head on.
Kini kau siap menghadapi fakta itu langsung.
But you are still running away from
Tapi kau masih lari
remembering the thoughts you had when you pulled the trigger.
dari mengingat-ingat isi pikiranmu saat menarik pelatuk.
You still see it, don't you?
Kau masih dihantui, 'kan?
That young man's ghost.
Bayang-bayang pemuda itu.
Yes.
Ya.
When you make everything clear and bring it all into the light,
Saat kau berhasil menelaah emosimu dan mengungkap semuanya,
that ghost will disappear as well.
bayang-bayang itu akan hilang.
"Bring it all into the light," huh?
"Mengungkap semuanya", ya?
The Murder Case of Holmer the Accountant.
Kasus pembunuhan Holmer, Akuntan.
The victim, Joachim Holmer, had built a steady career,
Korban, Joachim Holmer, memiliki karier yang stabil
and was not someone who would incur anyone's wrath.
dan bukan orang yang suka mencari musuh.
Yet he was stabbed repeatedly and nothing was even stolen.
Tapi dia ditusuk berulang kali, barang-barangnya tak dicuri.
The "Voice of God" Murder Case.
Kasus pembunuhan "Suara Tuhan".
The victims were a former maid and chauffeur.
Korbannya adalah mantan pelayan dan sopir.
On the wall of both crime scenes,
Di dinding kedua TKP,
the culprit scribbled a message. "I heard the voice of God."
pelaku menuliskan pesan. "Aku mendengar suara Tuhan."
The Dornach CEO Murder Case.
Pembunuhan CEO Dornach.
Ruud Gauck, a prominent person of wealth in Bavaria,
Ruud Gauck, salah satu jutawan ternama di Bayern,
was found dead in Hart-Holz forest.
ditemukan tewas di hutan Hart-Holz.
The Spieler Couple Murder Case.
Pembunuhan pasutri Spieler.
A drowned middle-aged couple were found floating in the upper Isar River.
Pasutri tersebut tenggelam dan ditemukan di hulu sungai Isar.
It is being investigated as one of the middle-aged couple serial murders.
Kini diselidiki sebagai pembunuhan berantai pasutri paruh baya.
The suspect, a Japanese doctor, is still at large.
Tersangka, dokter asal Jepang, masih buron.
What a mess.
Ya ampun.
As the unsolved cases grew in number, so did my alcohol intake.
Dulu makin banyak kasus tak terpecahkan, makin sering aku minum.
But now I'm different from back then.
Sekarang aku berubah.
I see. It's as the doctor said.
Aku paham. Seperti Dokter bilang,
So this is what he meant by thinking without drinking.
beginilah rasanya berpikir tanpa dipengaruhi alkohol.
What?
Apa?
Hold on a second.
Tunggu sebentar. Pikirkan baik-baik.
Think care--
Pikirkan…
So?
Jadi?
What was it that you remembered then?
Apa yang kau ingat saat itu?
Well, that's the thing.
Itulah masalahnya.
Something did come to mind, but…
Ada yang terpikirkan, tapi…
You saw that young man's ghost and your flash of inspiration vanished?
Saat melihat bayang-bayang pemuda itu, inspirasimu lenyap?
Yes.
Ya.
You needn't rush this.
Tak perlu buru-buru.
That flash of inspiration will come to you again soon enough.
Inspirasi itu pasti akan datang lagi.
What was it that came to mind?
Apa yang saat itu terlintas?
It felt like an important key to solving one of the unsolved cases.
Rasanya seperti kunci penting memecahkan salah satu kasus.
Just my imagination.
Cuma perasaanku.
Who's there?
Siapa itu?
Who's there? Who's following me?
Siapa itu? Siapa yang membuntutiku?
It's just like back then.
Seperti saat itu.
Back then, I was chasing him down in an alley like this…
Aku juga mengejarnya di gang seperti ini…
I'm sorry for visiting at this hour.
Maaf datang di luar jam praktik.
No, you're ready to talk about everything.
Tidak, kau siap mencurahkannya.
Let me hear it.
Aku ingin dengar.
At that moment, I could see inside that young man.
Saat itu, aku sekilas bisa memahami pemuda itu.
I learned that it existed in this world.
Aku paham hal itu nyata.
True evil.
Kejahatan sejati.
That's why I…
Karena itu…
That's why I shot down that young man.
Karena itu aku menembak pemuda itu.
Good, you did well in telling me.
Bagus, kau bisa mencurahkannya.
With this, you've really recovered.
Dengan ini, proses penyembuhanmu dimulai.
There's more.
Satu hal lagi.
I realized something.
Aku sadar.
Yes?
Apa?
What came to mind earlier…
Yang terlintas di pikiranku tadi…
All those unsolved cases that I had were actually
Ternyata semua kasus tak terpecahkan yang kuhadapi
just one case.
hanya satu kasus.
"Dear Dr. Gillen."
"Dokter Gillen yang terhormat.
"The book you sent me, Theory of Transcendent Criminal Psychology,
Buku kirimanmu, Teori Psikologi Kriminal Luar Biasa,
was a fascinating read."
adalah bacaan menarik.
"I feel great joy in knowing that a pupil I taught
Aku begitu senang karena mahasiswa yang kuajar
at  the University of Düsseldorf is actively working like this."
di Universitas Düsseldorf, sekarang aktif di bidangnya.
"By the way, Dr. Gillen,
Omong-omong, dr. Gillen,
in your interviews with Peter Jürgens, the serial killer you mentioned,
dalam wawancaramu dengan Peter Jürgens, pembunuh berantai yang kau bahas,
I believe he told you
dia sempat bilang
that he was ordered by a friend to commit the murder."
dia membunuh atas permintaan temannya.
"My memory is unclear, so could you please tell me once more
Aku tak terlalu ingat, bisa beri tahu sekali lagi
the name of Jürgens's friend?"
nama teman Jürgens?
"P.S."
N.B.
"You were an incredibly brilliant student during your college years,
Kau murid yang sangat cerdas saat kuliah,
but you had a classmate
tapi kau punya teman
who was brilliant enough to compete with you for the top rank."
yang mampu bersaing denganmu di peringkat atas.
"He continued on the path of becoming a brain surgeon,
Dia meneruskan kariernya menjadi dokter bedah saraf,
but now he is the suspect of a serial murder case."
tapi kini dia tersangka kasus pembunuhan berantai.
"Can you tell me whatever you know about him, however small it may be?"
Bisa ceritakan semua yang kau tahu tentangnya?
"What kind of person is he,
Dia orang seperti apa?
and where is he now?"
Di mana dia sekarang?
"The man named Dr. Tenma."
Pria bernama dr. Tenma."
Oh, you're the police detective from back then.
Kau penyidik yang dulu itu.
Well, now I'm a private investigator doing a variety of work.
Bukan, kini aku detektif swasta yang menerima berbagai permintaan.
I apologize for bringing up such a tough topic,
Maaf mengungkit topik tak mengenakkan,
but may I ask you one more time
tapi bolehkah kutanya sekali lagi
about the "Voice of God" Case where your mother was a victim?
tentang ibumu yang menjadi korban di kasus "Suara Tuhan"?
Of course.
Tentu saja.
After all, it has already been four years, and the police are no longer trying.
Sudah empat tahun berlalu dan polisi sudah berhenti menyelidikinya.
Schuwald?
Schuwald?
Yes.
Ya.
I believe your mother was a housekeeper for that wealthy individual.
Kalau tidak salah, ibumu pramuwisma orang kaya itu.
Yes, but that was 20 years ago.
Ya, tapi itu 20 tahun lalu.
Was there a reason why she quit?
Apa ada alasan dia berhenti?
She wasn't in great health at the time,
Dia kurang sehat.
and she'd only take jobs in the neighborhood after that.
Setelah itu, dia hanya bekerja di dekat rumah.
Could it be that things didn't go well with Mr. Schuwald?
Apakah ada konflik dengan Pak Schuwald?
That's unthinkable.
Tidak mungkin.
In fact, she loved to read poems.
Malah, ibuku suka membaca puisi.
She said when Mr. Schuwald could still see,
Katanya saat Pak Schuwald masih bisa melihat,
they'd often read aloud together.
mereka sering membaca bersama.
Oh, right. Please come this way.
Oh, ya. Silakan kemari.
See? Take a look.
Lihatlah.
I've kept them, as they're memories of my mother.
Kusimpan karena itu kenang-kenangan dari Ibu.
All of these poetry anthologies
Semua antologi puisi ini
were presents she received from Mr. Schuwald.
hadiah dari Pak Schuwald ke ibuku.
The ex-detective who was on the Dornach CEO Murder Case
Mantan penyidik yang mengurus kasus pembunuhan CEO Dornach
is now a private investigator, huh?
kini jadi detektif swasta, rupanya.
I wanted to speak once more with you, the CEO's former secretary,
Aku ingin menanyaimu lagi selaku mantan sekretaris CEO
about people who resented your CEO.
soal orang yang dendam kepada CEO-mu.
The CEO's enemies?
Musuh-musuh CEO, ya?
I told you there'd be no end if I started listing them.
Kalau kusebutkan, tak ada habisnya.
The list of companies that went bankrupt because of the CEO, Mr. Gauck,
Daftar perusahaan yang bangkrut karena CEO, Pak Gauck,
should already have been analyzed by the police long ago.
harusnya sudah diselidiki oleh polisi.
There is one more influential wealthy individual in Bavaria, yes?
Salah satunya jutawan berpengaruh di Bayern, ya?
What was his relationship with him?
Apa hubunganmu dengannya?
Do you mean Mr. Schuwald?
Maksudmu Pak Schuwald?
Well, of course, they were life-long rivals.
Tentu saja mereka rival bebuyutan.
Are you aware?
Kau tahu, tidak?
Schuwald has gone bankrupt twice in the past.
Schuwald pernah bangkrut dua kali.
The second time was the result
Kali kedua adalah akibat
of fierce business competition with Mr. Gauck.
persaingan bisnis sengit dengan Pak Gauck.
In other words, your CEO put Mr. Schuwald out of business.
Berarti Pak Gauck penyebab Pak Schuwald bangkrut.
But Schuwald has also put our CEO under before too.
Tapi Schuwald pernah membuat CEO kami gulung tikar juga.
Did they despise each other?
Keduanya saling benci?
Of course.
Tentu.
There'd be trouble when the two met occasionally at party venues,
Saat keduanya bertemu di pesta, kadang ada keributan.
baring their emotions as they'd quarrel with each other.
Mereka meluapkan emosi sambil bertengkar.
Those two did that?
Dua orang itu?
Yes, despite their cold nature.
Ya, padahal keduanya tipe orang yang kalem.
They could argue with nobody on an equal footing but each other.
Mereka satu-satunya kompetitor yang setara bagi satu sama lain.
Rather than rivals,
Daripada rival,
they were actually more like friends.
sebenarnya mereka lebih seperti teman.
Careful up there!
Hati-hati!
Yeah, he knew Hans very well.
Ya, dia kenal baik dengan Hans.
He was one of the two people killed in the "Voice of God" Case.
Dia salah satu orang yang mati di kasus "Suara Tuhan".
He was a good guy too. I feel sorry for him.
Padahal dia orang baik. Kasihan.
Was Hans really that nice?
Hans memang sebaik itu?
Yeah, he'd treat him to drinks often.
Ya, sering mentraktirku minum.
He used to work as Schuwald's chauffeur, right?
Dia bekas sopir Schuwald, 'kan?
Apparently.
Tampaknya.
But that was 30 years ago.
Tapi itu 30 tahun lalu.
Do you know why he was fired?
Kau tahu kenapa dia dipecat?
It's because Schuwald went bankrupt around then.
Karena Schuwald bangkrut.
Oh, I see.
Oh, begitu.
So it's not like there were any other issues?
Jadi, tak ada masalah lain?
Listen up.
Dengarkan.
I'm saying this to protect Hans's honor.
Ini kukatakan demi nama baik Hans.
It didn't matter if you were a rich bastard or a poor person like us.
Dia tak peduli kita kaya raya atau miskin.
He was a good guy who'd hang out with you no matter who you are.
Siapa pun kita, dia orang baik yang mau mengobrol dengan kita.
He'd often say
Hans sering bilang
that he was the one who taught the rich guy how to birdwatch.
dialah yang mengajari Schuwald cara mengamati burung.
Birdwatch?
Mengamati burung?
Yeah. He may be called a vampire, but when he took him to the woods,
Ya. Schuwald dijuluki vampir, tapi saat diajak ke hutan,
he'd get excited like a little boy.
dia antusias sekali seperti anak kecil.
Two years have already passed,
Sudah dua tahun berlalu,
yet whenever I think of my husband, I still…
tapi setiap aku ingat suamiku…
My husband was an earnest man.
Suamiku orang yang lurus.
There was no reason people would hold a grudge against him.
Tak mungkin ada alasan mendendam kepadanya.
Yet he was killed in such a manner…
Tapi dia malah dibunuh sekeji itu.
I can only imagine.
Aku turut prihatin.
I apologize, but I believe your husband was…
Maaf, kalau tidak salah, suamimu…
Yes, he was in an orphanage as a child.
Ya, saat kecil, dia di panti asuhan.
He moved from one foster home to another
Dia sering berganti rumah asuh
and became an accountant after all that hardship.
dan menjadi akuntan setelah semua cobaan itu.
Mr. Schuwald asked him to work as his accountant, yes?
Pak Schuwald menawarinya bekerja sebagai akuntannya, ya?
Yes, many times.
Ya, berulang kali.
But he would refuse.
Tapi suamiku menolak.
Not only was he busy with the work he had,
Selain sibuk dengan pekerjaannya,
but he said his philosophy regarding money was different from his own.
suamiku bilang filosofi mereka soal uang berseberangan.
My husband was adamant that the money be clean.
Suamiku berkeras uangnya harus bersih.
Thank you for your cooperation.
Terima kasih atas kerja samanya.
Will the culprit be caught?
Apa pelakunya akan tertangkap?
I'll do my best.
Aku akan berusaha.
I will catch him no matter what.
Pasti akan kutangkap pelakunya.
Goodbye.
Aku pamit.
-Oh, by the way… -Yes?
- Omong-omong… - Ya?
Do you know how your husband met him?
Kau tahu di mana suamimu dan Schuwald berkenalan?
Oh, he said they met in the woods.
Katanya mereka pertama kali bertemu di hutan.
In the woods?
Hutan?
It was when Mr. Schuwald could still see.
Ya, saat itu Pak Schuwald masih bisa melihat.
He ran into him in the woods.
Mereka bertemu di hutan.
Why was it in a place like that?
Kenapa bisa di tempat itu?
They were birdwatching.
Mereka mengamati burung.
They met many times after that.
Setelah itu, mereka sering bertemu.
Birdwatching…
Mengamati burung.
Excited like a little boy…
Antusias seperti anak kecil.
They'd read aloud together…
Mereka membaca bersama.
Friends…
Teman.
Are you okay?!
Kau tak apa?
Yes, I'm fine. Thank you.
Ya. Aku tak apa. Terima kasih.
What awful driving.
Sopir ngawur.
It almost looked like he was trying to hit you.
Dia seperti sengaja mau menabrakmu.
Dr. Reichwein, I've collected all the evidence.
Dokter Reichwein, aku sudah mengumpulkan bukti.
It was exactly as I told you the other day.
Seperti yang kukatakan tempo hari.
The many cases I had when I was a police detective
Kasus-kasus yang kutangani selama jadi penyidik,
were all pointing in the same direction.
semua arahnya sama.
The "Voice of God" Murder Case.
Kasus pembunuhan "Suara Tuhan".
The Dornach CEO Murder Case.
Kasus pembunuhan CEO Dornach.
The Accountant Murder Case.
Kasus pembunuhan akuntan.
At first glance, these cases seem unrelated to each other.
Sepintas, kasus-kasus ini tak terkait.
The modus operandi are all different too.
Modus operandinya berbeda-beda.
The victims aren't connected
Para korban tak saling kenal
and they're not related monetarily in any way either.
dan tak ada kaitan secara finansial,
Thus, there was one truth that didn't exist on record.
tapi ada satu fakta yang tak tercatat.
There was one point that connected them all.
Benang merah dari semua kasus.
Each victim's death
Setiap kematian korban
forced Schuwald into solitude.
memaksa Schuwald untuk menyendiri.
And there was one more strange commonality.
Dan ada satu lagi kesamaan yang aneh.
In the Dornach CEO Murder Case,
Di kasus pembunuhan CEO Dornach,
right before the crime,
sebelum insiden terjadi,
Mr. Gauck left, saying he was going to an important business meeting.
Pak Gauck pergi ke rapat bisnis penting.
The name of the person he was to meet,
Nama orang yang akan dia temui
and the name of the god written on the walls in the "Voice of God" Case.
sama dengan nama Tuhan yang ditulis di tembok pada kasus "Suara Tuhan".
And the middle-aged couple serial murder,
Ada pula kasus pembunuhan berantai pasutri paruh baya,
the only case that seemed unrelated to the other cases I had.
itu satu-satunya kasus yang tampaknya tak terkait.
The culprit's name that was stated during the investigation by a suspect,
Tapi saat penyidikan, tersangkanya, dokter asal Jepang,
the Japanese doctor.
menyebutkan nama pelakunya.
They were all the same name.
Di semua kasus itu, muncul nama yang sama.
Johan.
Johan.
A former pupil of mine, a criminal psychologist,
Mantan mahasiswaku, ahli psikolog kriminal,
was researching a serial killer who was ordered by a friend to kill.
meneliti pembunuh berantai yang membunuh atas perintah temannya.
He told me of this in his letter.
Dia menceritakannya di surat ini.
The name of that friend was also
Nama teman itu juga…
Johan.
Johan.
It's a common name.
Itu nama pasaran.
The connection between the cases is nothing more than a guess.
Hubungan antara kasusnya juga baru asumsi.
But if this is indeed the truth,
Tapi jika ini faktanya,
it would mean this Johan strategically committed serial murders
berarti Johan secara strategis mendalangi pembunuhan berantai
for the past four years to push Schuwald into total isolation.
selama empat tahun terakhir demi mengisolasi Schuwald.
And Margot Langer, the one who birthed Schuwald's son, is conveniently dead.
Margot Langer, yang melahirkan putra Schuwald, juga tiba-tiba mati.
The student, Fahren, who claimed to be Schuwald's son,
Fahren, mahasiswa yang mengaku putra Schuwald,
conveniently killed himself when the real son appeared.
juga tiba-tiba bunuh diri saat putra kandungnya muncul.
If he really does exist,
Jika Johan benar-benar ada,
where is this Johan now?
di mana dia sekarang?
I see. Johan is also here?
Oh, ya? Johan juga di sini?
Hi, Johan. What lovely weather we have today.
Hai, Johan. Cuaca hari ini cerah, ya?
Yes, it's very nice.
Ya, cerah sekali.
He's right next to Schuwald.
Dia ada di dekat Schuwald!
Execution
Terjemahan subtitle oleh Rizky Soraya